hey everyone today I want to talk about
Optical interferometry a method that is
frequently used to measure the
properties of optical components and
systems
what initially made me want to do a
video about this subject is this zygo
interferometer that I bought a while ago
secondhand
a new instrument of this type is
financially far out of my reach and I
must admit that this one wasn't a
bargain either but the thing is I wanted
to own a high quality interferometer for
a long time if only to get away from the
do-it-yourself setups that I've used so
far and since these instruments are not
abundantly available secondhand I just
had to take this rare opportunity to buy
one
in case you have no idea what this
instrument is with it you can very
accurately measure the shape of flat and
spherical Optical interfaces like the
ones you find on lenses and mirrors and
with accurately I mean in the nanometer
range
but not only that you can also measure
the performance of complete Optical
systems so a good interferometer is an
indispensable tool for anyone involved
in Optical fabrication because in the
end the quality of your Optics is mainly
limited by the quality of your testing
methods
this particular instrument was produced
by zygo in August of 1996 it was sold to
Philips Electronics in Eindhoven where
it was used to check the surface shape
of lenses of special Optical disk drives
from what I understood some of these
lenses were produced from small polished
glass balls and these were cut in pieces
and then transformed into very short
focal distance lenses now at some point
the activity was transferred to a
Phillips spin-off called anterion and
the interferometer was sold to an
employee who basically stored it for a
couple of years he then sold it to me
together with a black and white Monitor
and the transmission sphere that was
used to test the lenses
in this video I'll first discuss the
principle behind interferometry and then
we'll take a look at the layout of the
instrument and how it works exactly and
in an upcoming video I'll show you how I
pimped the instrument a bit with a
modern CCD camera
as I said earlier in Optics manufacturer
interferometry is a frequently used
method to characterize both Optical
surfaces as well as complete systems and
the method is based on analyzing
interference patterns and extract
so-called wavefront information from
them and I will discuss the meaning of
the word wavefront in a second
interferometry is an extremely sensitive
and accurate method that can be used to
establish the general shape of an
interface but also things like waviness
or even surface roughness it does also
have some limitations the measurement
ranges generally fairly limited to
several microns also it's unsuitable for
interfaces that contain sharp step-like
height features because these cannot be
unambiguously identified and so in
general interferometry is most accurate
when the surfaces we want to test are
fairly smooth
now I just mentioned the word wavefront
which I think is not a trivial concept I
guess we've all experienced wavefronts
at some points in our lives but I'm not
referring to those in Optics away from
this actually a continuous set of points
that have identical phase so what does
that mean well from a classical
Viewpoint light is an electromagnetic
wave that harmonically oscillates and
propagates in space and at any given
point in this process the electric and
magnetic field components can be
described by the Maxwell equations so
here I've tried to schematically draw
the electromagnetic field in a somewhat
larger volume and if you examine the
phase of these waves you can identify
planes where the face of the
electromagnetic field is identical and
the continuous set of points that have
the same phase value is called away
front
one property of a wavefront is that its
shape is always transverse or
perpendicular to the local direction of
wave propagation here this is
Illustrated for a few differently shaped
wavefronts where the arrows indicate the
direction of wave propagation now in
general phase relationships for
different points in space are only well
defined when the waves have one specific
wavelength and if we want to do
interferometry it's vital that the light
we use is of one particular wavelength
which is also called monochromatic light
and in the rest of this video I'll
assume that the light used is more or
less monochromatic
a frequently used way to generate
monochromatic radiation is by means of a
laser and this is because the process of
stimulated emission which takes place in
the laser cavity favors the generation
of light in a very narrow wavelength
range also the wavefront exiting the
laser cavity is virtually flat over the
aperture and because the light has an
extremely well defined wavelength in
other words it has a very narrow
spectral bandwidth phase relationships
in the field exiting the laser can be
preserved over long distances
another way to say this is that lasers
have a long coherence length which is
generally between half a meter up to
several kilometers for certain special
types of lasers
in practice this means that if we take
two points A and B in the light path and
we look at the variations in the phase
difference between the two points we
will find that these will be relatively
small and the distance over which
variations in Phase remain acceptable is
called the coherence length as you can
see from this equation the coherence
length LC is inversely proportional to
the spectral bandwidth Delta Nu of the
light source and so light sources with a
very narrow emission line will generally
have a long coherence length
another source of monochromatic light
frequently used in interferometry is the
low pressure sodium lamp which mainly
generates light in a narrow emission
band at 589 nanometers however the
spectral bandwidth of the sodium
emission line is much broader than that
of lasers and the phase relationships
generally only hold over distances
smaller than a millimeter
now measuring the shape of a waveform
directly in the visible part of the
electromagnetic spectrum is not easy and
that is because of the high frequencies
involved for electromagnetic radiation
of longer wavelengths like for example
radio waves we can measure the phase of
the alternating Fields directly and that
is because the oscillations have
relatively low frequency say generally
somewhere in the mega or gigahertz range
and so we can point a bunch of antennas
to the sky measure the electromagnetic
signals that are received in each of
them and then establish the shape of the
wavefront for a particular frequency by
looking for phase correlations and based
on this information we can identify the
exact direction from which the radiation
is emitted
but the visible light has a frequency
more than a thousand times higher than
even the highest frequency radio waves
and for frequencies this high it's
technically infeasible to measure phase
directly for an oscillating
electromagnetic field
however what we can easily measure with
Optical detectors like CCD or CMOS
sensors is spatial intensity variations
and that is where interferometry comes
in instead of trying to measure the
phase in light directly this method
works by studying the interference
patterns resulting from the addition of
a second wavefront that has a known
shape
let me start by showing you a very
simple example of how this works in
light
for this experiment we need a
monochromatic light source and a flat
surface as a light source we'll use a
sodium lamp and for the surface we'll
use a flat Optical test glass
now a typical air gloss interface
reflects about four percent of the
incident light and with a uniform light
source we observe a uniform reflection
let's now place two differently shaped
surfaces on top of this reference
surface for evaluation and what we now
observe is that these objects show two
different interference patterns the part
of the left shows straight lines with
equal spacing and I wanted to write this
place these curved lines or circular
fringes depending on the exact surface
orientation now it's these intensity
variations that actually contain
detailed information about the
difference in shape between the
reference surface and the two surfaces
under tests and we just need to know how
to interpret what we see exactly
so what do we see well let me explain
with an animation I admit the following
is a simplification and it's not
correctly visualizing the physics but
it's actually quite illustrative here is
away from that has just reflected off a
flat reference surface so this wavefront
is basically also flat and so the image
shows a 2d cross-section of the flat
Optical wavefront
now we place a sensor in the path of the
light we can measure the intensity and
what we observe is that it's basically
the same everywhere and this tells us
exactly nothing about the shape of the
wavefront
now let's add a second wavefront that
has reflected of a second surface that
is slightly tilted in this example the
wavefront is also flat and what we
observe is that the intensity now
becomes non-uniform and this is caused
by constructive and destructive
interference between the two reflected
wavefronts at the second interface here
the electromagnetic field is the linear
sum of the contributions of the fields
of the two wavefronts and so in some
points where these contributions are
always in Phase they add up on the other
hand in places where the two are exactly
out of phase the field contributions
cancel each other out and if they are of
equal amplitude effectively the
resulting field becomes zero
in the case of two flat wavefronts we
will observe linear and equally spaced
fringes and the density of the
interference pattern itself is dependent
on the wedge or angle between the two
surfaces and the position of the fringes
is dependent on the distance between the
two surfaces now you might think that
linear and equally spaced fringes are
indicative for the presence of two flat
surfaces and that's partly correct but
two curved wavefronts with exactly the
same radius of curvature will actually
also display linear and equally spaced
fringes when displays are tilted
however when two waveforms have
different radii this results in curve
fringes and this is for example the case
when we have a flat and a spherical
wavefront interfering or when we have
two spherical waveforms that have a
different radius of curvature so I guess
it's important to realize that the
observed interference pattern only gives
us information about differences in
wavefront shape
the example just shown with the Sodium
lamp we only observe interference
between the interfaces when they're
placed very close together and that is
because of the limited coherence length
of the light so whether we can see a
clear interference pattern is dependent
on whether stable phase relationships
exists between the reflections coming
off the two surfaces at the point where
they start interfering and this means
that with a coherence length smaller
than a millimeter the surfaces need to
be quite close to each other in order to
observe interference fringes
now I just stated that in constructive
interference the electromagnetic fields
add up and in destructive interference
the two contributions cancel each other
out so what does this mean for intensity
well light intensity is equivalent to
the power per unit of surface and so
it's actually not the same thing as the
magnitude of the electronic field in
fact intensity scales with the square of
this field and so if we have two
reflections of equal magnitude say both
are four percent this means that for the
location of constructive interference
the intensity could be four times as
high and that is actually what is
generally observed in interference
patterns that the intensity in the
bright areas is much brighter than the
sum of the two individual intensities
but of course if we look on average the
intensity over the whole area will still
be equal to the sum of the two
individual intensities
anyway enough background let's return to
the zygote interferometer itself and
take a peek under the hood to see what's
going on inside
in order to do that we need to remove
two different Lids the outer one is made
of plastic and it's basically just
cosmetic and the second one is made out
of aluminum sheet metal and it is
intended as RF shielding for the
electronics inside
the first thing you notice is that it
isn't awfully full inside there is a
helium neon laser with its high voltage
power supply then there are a few
Optical components like a steering
mirror for a laser beam a variable
filter that can be moved mechanically
using a rod and this Rod also operates a
switch that activates either of two PCB
cameras that can also be found in this
top part of the interferometer
and the cameras by the way have CCD
chips of about four by six millimeter in
size and are fairly low resolution
now both cameras have lenses mounted in
front of them and one of the cameras is
above a tiny beam splitter and the other
one is above a diffuser with a Crosshair
printed on it
in the bottom compartment behind the lid
here we find the mains 12 volt DC power
supply a large beam splitter a mirror
under 45 degrees and a four inch
collimation lens and apart from a few
brackets and mounts that hold the Optics
together that is basically it
so you might wonder why was this thing
the price of a luxury car back in 1996
well apart from I suspect a healthy
profit margin there are several reasons
of course it's not really a mass
manufactured item but another reason is
that every component inside appears to
be of very high quality take for example
the helium neon laser according to the
label the tube has been specifically
selected for this type of instrument why
well if we look at the specification of
the coherence length of the
interferometer we see that it's larger
than 100 meters this means that the
wavelength variations in the laser light
need to be extremely low so that the
phase relationships hold over distances
of more than 100 meters now I calculated
what this means in terms of frequency
stability and found that variations in
the frequency of the light cannot be
more than 2 times 10 to the minus seven
percent and so this means that not just
any random laser will do
so let me take you through the
functionality of all the optical
components step by step using schematics
here is the helium mule laser which
outputs a highly coherent beam of light
and the direction of the beam can be
optimized with this small steering
mirror after which the beam goes through
a variable attenuation filter now this
filter allows for adjustment of the
general brightness of the laser beam and
after having passed the attenuation
filter the beam is going into a gradient
index lens which is connected to a very
small beam splitter
now a gradient index lens is a small
glass rod that contains a gradient in
refractive index that runs from the
center to the edge of the rod and since
the refractive index has the highest
value in the center the optical
wavefront in the laser beam is gradually
delayed more towards the center of the
rod and the waveform therefore becomes
curved which effectively results in
focusing of the light into a tight focal
point and after passing this focal point
the beam expands again into a nicely
spherical wavefront
a small beam splitter sends the
spherical waveform into the partially
reflective surface of a second much
larger beam splitter and this surface
reflects the light towards a collimation
lens where the light exits the
instrument
the function of the collimation lens is
to convert the spherical wavefront into
a flat wavefront of four inches in
diameter and this flat waveform can
serve as the basis for all kinds of
interferometric tests for example we can
place two partially reflective flat
interfaces into this output beam one
being the reference interface and one
being the interface that we'd like to
test for flatness and due to the large
coherence length of the light more than
100 meters these interfaces don't have
to be necessarily very close together
the light reflecting of these surfaces
is directed back into the interferometer
approximately along the same path as it
came from goes through a small beam
splitter again and then is collimated
and projected on the CCD chip and this
allows us to observe the interference
pattern between the two Reflections and
evaluate this visually on the monitor
now to steer the light off both the
reference and test surface exactly back
through the tiny beam splitter here is
pretty hard and you don't see anything
with camera one until things are almost
perfectly aligned so to make life a lot
easier the people at zygo edit this
alignment functionality to the system
part of the light from the reflections
can pass this larger beam splitter and
this part continues straight on it's
reflected at 90 degrees angle and then
reaches the glass diffuser plate that
contains a Crosshair pattern
because this diffuser plate is exactly
at the focal distance of the collimation
lens the reflections create tiny spots
here and their positions can be observed
by camera 2 that is only intended for
alignment purposes now this alignment
unit has a much larger field of view and
what we can do now is simply align the
position of the surface reflection such
that they are at the center of the
Crosshair and when that's the case the
system is also automatically aligned on
camera one we can immediately observe an
interferogram
now the interferometers that I made
myself did not have this kind of feature
and I must admit that this really makes
aligning Optics a piece of cake
here you see the location of the
collimation lens viewed from the outside
of the instrument in front of it is an
adjustment mechanism that is intended
for mounting various reference surfaces
to the interferometer directly like for
example the f.7 D5 transmission sphere
that came with interferometer
the adjustment mechanism has two degrees
of freedom which are tip and tilt and
this allows the angle of the
transmission reference to be oriented
with respect to the surface under test
so when testing Optical components you
generally test the surface shape before
the interfaces get coated and so in the
case of glosses means that they reflect
around four percent of the incident
light
so the transmission reference also needs
to reflect around four percent back into
the interferometer to get high contrast
fringes
not to test spherical surfaces you need
a spherical reference surface that
somehow reflects four percent of the
light exiting the infrometer right back
into the instrument
here I've drawn a schematic of the
inside of a transmission sphere assembly
to show you how that is achieved
the reference surface is the last
interface of the assembly here indicated
in yellow and all the other surfaces are
anti-reflection coated for the laser
wavelength
but even more importantly they're also
designed in such a way that the Light
reaches the reference interface exactly
perpendicular and this means that it's
the only interface in the transmission
sphere that sends a reflection back
where it came from and then enters the
interferometer as a collimated beam and
of course
96 of the light continues onto the
surface under test which also reflects
around four percent and so we observe
the interference occurring between these
two interfaces
with a spherical transmission reference
we can test convex as well as concave
optics for convex Optics only radii is
smaller than the radius of the
transmission sphere itself can be tested
and for concave Optics the only
limitation for the radius to be tested
is that it should be less than half of
the maximum coherence length of the
light source that we use which is in
this case 50 meters
now I want to save most of the
experiments that I had in mind for
another video but let's just do one
simple experiment for this test we'll
just use the flat wavefront exiting the
instrument and what we'll try to measure
is the difference in shape between the
two surfaces of a zero to your test
Clause this test class has one side
which I know is very flat around 120th
of a wavelength and this is going to be
our reference interface but the other
side is somewhat less flat and what
we'll try to find out is how much that
is
the two interfaces are spaced 20
millimeters apart and both reflect
around four percent of the incident
light so we can just place the disc in
the beam exiting the interferometer
align the position of the two
Reflections simultaneously and then look
at the interference pattern and this is
what it looks like as you can see we get
a nice and clear interference pattern
which by the way is extremely stable
with no effects of vibrations from the
environment and that is because the two
surfaces are basically mechanically
connected to each other by a solid piece
of zero Doer
now the small circular spots are just
dust particles in the optical path and
these are not important for our
evaluation
all the information about the different
in shape and orientation between the two
surfaces is contained in the four more
or less vertical fringes and because we
know that one side is almost perfectly
flat any curvature in The Fringe pattern
is a result of non-flatness of the
second interface
so let's try to evaluate this pattern
visually the most obvious feature is of
course the presence of the four vertical
fringes that indicate that there is a
wedge between the two interfaces in the
horizontal Direction and we can evaluate
how large this wedge is based on the
number of fringes it's a little over
four lobda wavefront meaning that there
is a wedge half of that between the two
surfaces so just two wavelengths y half
well that is because in reflection any
deviations in surface shape lead to
twice the deviation in the wave front
shape and so deviations in the surface
shape are only half of that observed in
the wavefront
now since the wavelength of the laser is
633 nanometers and the wedge is two
lobbed up between the two surfaces this
would mean a gradient in distance of
approximately 1.3 microns but there is a
little catch in this case because we are
comparing two surfaces with zero during
between them we should actually use the
wavelength in this material which means
that we should divide the wavelength in
air or vacuum by the refractive index of
zero deer which is 1.54
so this means that the wedge is actually
only 840 nanometers but which side is
thicker it's actually quite hard to tell
as for which we would see the same type
of interference pattern in either case
so at this point we just don't know
okay let's for a moment focus on the
curvature of the fringes now which
indicates a difference in the radius
between the two surfaces and if we look
at how much the curvature in the fringes
deviates from straight lines we see that
it's largest here in the center it's
about 0.4 times The Fringe spacing which
translates to 0.4 wavelengths of height
difference between the edge and the
center of the disc
for the surface error which again is
half of that we find 0.2 wavelengths now
since we also need to use the wavelength
inside zero do here this means that the
surface curvature is 0.2 times the
wavelength divided by the refractive
index which results in a value of 82
nanometers
but in which direction is the curve is
the surface under test 82 nanometers
concave or convex as for the direction
of the wedge there is no easy way to
tell so now we end up with these four
configurations of which only one can be
correct
with a little logic though you could at
this point already discard two of these
as infeasible but of course you want to
know exactly which configuration of the
four is correct right
so if that's indeed the case figure it
out yourself you just need two more
pieces of information here is a first
hint if I press my finger against the
back side of the disk so the service and
the test we can observe that the
interferogram changes due to the
temperature increase of the material by
the heat of my finger locally it's only
a few degrees Celsius higher but the
effect is very noticeable because we are
measuring in the nanometer range
now the second piece of information you
need is about the expansion coefficient
of the material as you can see from the
specifications of zero zero it can be
either positive or negative
but this piece of 02 has a positive
coefficient of thermal expansion which
means it expands with temperature
increase and with these two additional
pieces of information it's possible to
tell which of these four options is
correct now the first person to make a
comment with the correct answer and of
course why owns the pinned comment
okay so the letter was a very brief
explanation of how you can evaluate
interferograms visually and the above
example was actually relatively easy
imagine your interferogram looks
something like this or this in these
cases it would be quite a bit more
challenging to make accurate statements
about the exact surface shape
and this is why in the next video about
the subject I have replaced the current
analog camera with a high resolution IP
camera and this allows for a very
detailed evaluation of the
interferograms using software
with the help of this software we can
measure wedges angles surface curvature
and even the effect of warm fingers very
accurately also we'll take a look at how
to measure the shape of various Optical
surfaces and the quality of lens
assemblies so hopefully I'll see you in
the next video again
[Music]
thank you
bye bye
----------------------------------------------------------------------
# Optical Interferometry Part 2 - Measuring Optics with a Zygo GPI LC
hey everyone
today I want to demonstrate how the zygo
interferometer that I bought a few
months ago can be used to test Optics in
the previous video I explained how
interferometry Works what a wavefront is
and discuss the layout of the instrument
if you're unfamiliar with interferometry
and you haven't seen the previous video
it might be a good idea to watch that
one first
this video became quite long so here's
an overview of the contents which allows
you to skip ahead if you don't want to
watch everything first I'll show how I
replace the original low resolution
camera of the zygote with a modern IP
camera to record high resolution
interferograms and then we'll take a
quick look at how we can use the camera
in combination with the software called
DFT Fringe to create detailed wavefront
maps
the interferometer came with a reference
transmission sphere but unfortunately
the waveform documentation of this item
was missing so to do meaningful
measurements with it we first need to
establish its accuracy by performing a
calibration and with that done we can
test some actual Optics we'll examine
the surface properties of a high quality
concave wafer scanner mirror from the
1970s then we'll take a look at the
wavefront quality of a vintage Canon F
1.2 lens from the early 1980s will do
the same for a modern full-frame Canon
EF zoom lens and in the last part of the
video I'll show you measurements on the
optical properties of a couple of
microscope objectives all in all there's
quite a lot to cover so let's Dive Right
In
as shown in the previous video the
interferometer is a somewhat basic
version that displayed low resolution
black and white images on a monitor for
visual evaluation the instrument
contained two cameras one for the
alignment of the Optics under test and
one for displaying the interferogram
both cameras had a rather limited
resolution of 320 times 240 pixels now
since this is not 1996 anymore we can
now do quite a bit better than that
for the new camera to record the
interferograms I wanted to use a housed
camera with some kind of Mount to be
able to attach various types of lenses
and if you look at the layout of the
instrument there's actually plenty of
space to place such a camera in the
instrument right here we just need to
redirect the light in the horizontal
Direction so what I did was remove the
old camera and the lens and then made a
bracket that can hold a first surface
mirror under 45 degrees and this mirror
redirects the vertical beam to a
horizontal one which can then be
captured by the camera I tried different
kinds of lenses and eventually settled
on this compact 25 millimeter C mount
lens that works for most situations it's
able to capture the full field of the
interferometer while at the same time
covering a fairly large area of the
camera chip but of course for specific
measurements it's possible to use other
lenses like lenses with a longer focal
length or a variable zoom lens and this
can be very useful if you want to take a
look at small details in interferograms
by the way I left the original alignment
camera where it was because it still
works fine and you actually don't need a
lot of resolution to do the alignment
so the original monitor is still used in
the setup but only during alignment
procedures
for powering the IP camera I connected
it to a 12 volt power supply already
present in the instrument and after that
there was just one more thing to do and
that was bringing the camera's UTP
connection to the housing of the
instrument and for this purpose I used a
two-sided UTP female connector one side
connects to the camera the other side
connects to a PC and with that the
conversion is complete
now I used an IDs ethernet camera for
the conversion but in fact any camera
will do as long as it can be accessed
from a computer and the images can be
stored to disk so to capture the data
what I do is I align the optic to be
measured such that a clear interferogram
is visible with well-defined fringes it
helps if the camera software has a
feature to monitor the maximum Fringe
intensity so that we can adjust it to
within the linear dynamic range of the
camera then I collect the number of
interferograms with somewhat different
Fringe angles and spacings and these can
then serve as the basis for a wavefront
analysis
for the actual wavefront calculations
we'll use a free software called DFT
Fringe it's programmed by Dale Eason who
took it upon himself to make advanced
interferometry accessible to the masses
it's designed with amateur telescoping
in mind but as will become clear its
application range is quite a bit broader
than that I won't delve into all the
functionality of the software instead
I'll just very quickly walk you through
the process of evaluating interferograms
and averaging wavefronts
so here is the start screen of DFT
Fringe and before you can evaluate the
inferiograms correctly a program
requires the input of a few settings
like what wavelength is used and what
The Fringe spacing in the interferogram
actually represents now in some
configurations each Fringe represents
one wavelength of phase shift but in
others like in Auto collimation this
value actually needs to be set to 0.5
and when all the parameters are set
we're basically ready to go
the software gets us to our results in a
few steps you start by importing a
recorded interferogram and Define the
areas you wish to include or exclude in
the wavefront evaluation
if that's done the software performs a
2d Fourier transform on the selected
area and allows us to do a bit of low
frequency spatial filtering this
filtering can for example remove low
spatial frequencies that are the result
of the global intensity variations due
to an even illumination over the full
surface and after setting the low
frequency spatial filtering the image is
resampled to a specific size and from
this the software calculates the
waveform data
when the software calculates the
wavefront it also fits the data to a
specific set of known aberrations this
feature allows for removing specific
aberrations from your analysis for
example tilt is generally not an
aberration of interest because it
describes the orientation between the
reference and the wavefront under test
and so it has nothing to do with the
shape of either surface now DFD Fringe
allows you to either include or exclude
it from your analysis
you can customize the presentation of
the results and the scale you can also
for example convert wavefront errors to
surface shape errors and choose to
represent them in nanometers instead of
waves all in all this is a very useful
tool for interferometric Fringe analysis
and on top of that it can be downloaded
for free
in all the upcoming experiments I will
use this F 0.75 transmission sphere as a
reference and as I mentioned in the
introduction we don't know anything
about its accuracy of shape so before we
can measure any meaningful results with
it we need to measure the accuracy of
the reference sphere first but how do we
do that we could of course calibrate the
surface of the transmission sphere by
comparing its shape to a more precise
reference surface but instead I want to
show you another method known as the
random Ball Method
the method requires the use of a small
smooth ball with a reflective surface
the surface of the ball doesn't need to
be perfectly spherical but I guess it
helps if it's quite close to spherical
now the only thing we need to do for the
experiment is to measure the surface
shape of the ball at many random
positions with the reference sphere and
then average these measurements now the
reason that this works is that if you
collect a lot of samples from a bowl
surface even if it's far from perfect
all the errors in the individual parts
of the surface will eventually average
out and the average will iterate to a
surface equivalent of a perfect sphere
and when you get to that point the only
error that remains is the surface error
in the reference sphere because it's
systematically present in all the
individual measurements
you can buy these special high accuracy
silicon carbide balls for this purpose
and these are pretty expensive however
there's a much cheaper way I just used a
Precision aluminum oxide bearing ball
that typically costs less than let's say
25 Euros online
the largest balls generally have a
diameter of around 10 millimeters and
have a variation in the diameter of
about one micron so they're not
incredibly precise but as you will see
precise enough for this experiment
to hold the ball I made a stand from
three quarter inch bearing balls glued
on top of an aluminum rod using epoxy
and now we have a calibration setup
ready for less than 30 Euros
calibration procedure itself involves
placing this ball at the center of the
radius of curvature of the transmission
sphere in some random orientation we
record an interferogram then choose a
different random area on the ball record
another one and so on
and here is what evaluating the results
looks like in Practice What You observe
is that in the individual measurements
the surface area is generally larger
than a quarter of lobda and it's
actually all over the place and this is
due to the errors present in the shape
of the ball but look what happens when
we start averaging these measurements
after 10 measurements the error has
basically dropped down to a tenth of a
lobda peaked Valley and by adding more
and more measurements to the average we
can gradually bring this down even
further until after evaluating about 50
interferograms we do not see Improvement
anymore in the result and at that point
we know that the error that remains is
basically the error in the transmission
sphere reference
if we look at the accuracy of shape in
the spherical reference it's about 1
20th of a wavelength peaked Valley and
we will consider this to be the
wavefront accuracy over the full area of
the transmission sphere
now in all the upcoming tests we will
only use a small fraction of this
reference surface which will make the
accuracy of the tests quite a bit higher
than 1 20th of a lot
DFD Fringe presents the value of the
strail ratio quite prominently and I
actually discussed sterile ratio in
another video I must admit still ratio
is not the most common parameter used in
the specification of the optical quality
of for example lenses but for specifying
wavefront performance close to the
diffraction limit I think it's a very
useful parameter what it describes is
basically just the ratio between where
wave energy actually ends up in the
image compared to where it should have
ended up if the optic were perfect
so here's a graph of an intensity
profile of an imperfect optic and of a
perfect optic now to calculate this
Trail we take the area that is under
both curves and name it B and then
divide this by the area under the
perfect curve so area a and this
represents the fraction of the light
energy that goes where it should have
gone in an image
since Trail ratio is a fraction its
value is between 0 and 1 and the value
of 1 only applies to an object that
performs at the theoretical limit now
roughly speaking an optic with a trail
ratio value above 0.83 is considered to
be diffraction Limited what this doesn't
mean is that the optic is performing
perfectly in this region it just means
that the dominant factor for reduced
sharpness is because of diffraction for
example because of a limited aperture
and to a lesser degrees due to
imperfections and things like a surface
shape so in a sense the value of 0.83 is
similar to stating that a quarter
overlapped up Peak to Value wavefront
error is diffraction limited because
both these values are kind of arbitrary
definitions of what is meant by
diffraction Limited
so our reference surface turns out to be
very accurate as we can conclude from
both this Trail value as well as from
the peak to Valley wavefront error but
of course that is kind of essential if
you want to use it to measure Optical
quality of other objects in the high end
of the range
the first thing we're going to measure
is the surface shape of this spherical
zero deer mirror it's about 250
millimeters in diameter and it has a
radius of curvature of 350 millimeters I
bought the mirror about 10 years ago on
eBay for around 100 euros the reflective
coating was in pretty bad shape so I
removed it but the remaining surface
reflectivity is four percent which is
ideal in this test setup the mirror
itself is from a 1970s broken Elmer
wafer scanner system and this was the
first commercial photolithographic
system that used non-contact exposure of
silicon Wafers so given its original
application you'd expect this mirror to
be quite accurate
the way we measure this mirror is with
the focus of the reference element in
the center of the radius of curvature of
the mirror so the tightly focused Light
Beam from the interferometer expands and
then reflects off the mirror surface and
then returns along approximately the
same path and is recombined with the
spherical reference wavefront that
reflects off the reference element and
any deviations from spherical in the
mirror surface will cause phase shifts
between the light reflecting of the
mirror surface and the spherical
reference and this can then be observed
as interference
here are a few typical interferograms
that were measured with this mirror
under a slight tilt and even though the
mirror is strongly curved you can
observe that in the measurements it only
covers about half the diameter of the
total measurement area available this
makes our accuracy of measurement much
higher than a 20th of a wavelength
so from the interferograms just
collected the waveform differences
between the mirror surface and that of
the reference element is calculated in
DFD Fringe and you can see that the peak
to Value accuracy of this mirror itself
is around one tenth of a wavelength now
in terms of surface shape accuracy this
means that the mirror never deviates
more than around 30 nanometers of that
of a perfect sphere
anyway being able to measure with this
level of precision is actually pretty
cool and it gave me confidence that the
instrument performs as expected
by the way if you've ever tried to make
a telescope Mirror by hand yourself you
might observe something familiar in the
wavefront plot The Mirror Has a slightly
turned down Edge although this one's
very small around 15 nanometers or so
next on the list of items to test is
this Canon FD 55 millimeter F 1.2 lens
this is a rather famous vintage lens in
the sense that it was actually the first
consumer lens containing an aspherical
element
with its F 1.2 aperture it's very light
sensitive and therefore well suited for
indoor photography without using a flash
the earliest versions of this lens
introduced in 1971 contained radioactive
thorium oxide but this one which was
bought by my father in March of 1980
does not contain thorium therefore it
also does not display the characteristic
radiation Browning observed in
radioactive lenses and on top of that it
has lift in the Box most of it's live so
it's a nearly pristine condition
for testing the waveform deformation in
this lens we utilize a configuration
called Auto collimation which is
schematically depicted here because the
light passes through the lens twice in
this test many aberrations are measured
to be twice as large as they would be
with a single pass so when this
configuration is used it requires us to
interpret The Fringe spacing as
equivalent to only 0.5 wavelength
instead of one wavelength
before I show you the results of the
measurement I should mention that doing
away front measurement on a lens is not
in any way representative for overall
lens performance basically we're testing
with only one particular wavelength of
light on the optical axis with the focus
setting to Infinity so factors like
chromatic aberrations of axis
performance in the image field and at
proximity are not included in this test
I've actually made a video on how to
quantitatively measure all these aspects
using another method and obtain a more
holistic performance but even with all
the limitations I think it's worthwhile
to take a look at the wavefront error
that this lens introduces
so here is the wavefront error of the
lens at its full aperture and as you can
see it's actually pretty large the total
peaked Valley wavefront error is more
than three lobda and the most apparent
errors are spherical aberration and some
astigmatism
the streel ratio is actually quite
disappointing as well
now as a consequence this lens can never
provide High sharpness images at the
maximum aperture
now it's interesting to see what happens
if we limit the aperture of this lens to
let's say F4 and by doing that we'll
lose a lot of light about 90 percent but
this also limits the wavefront error to
the one present in this central part
here so if we do the same wavefront
analysis at F4 suddenly the lens
performs the fraction limited because
reducing aperture to F4 eliminates
almost all of the spherical error and
astigmatism which is present in the
wavefront at full aperture
here's a comparison of the text on a
permanent marker shot with f 1.2 and f4
on an aps-c sensor it's clear that the
three laptop wavefront arrow is
influencing the sharpness and contrast
pretty badly so I guess the only way to
use this lens effectively is to always
set it to a smaller aperture whenever
there's sufficient light available
otherwise you'll end up with very soft
images
the Canon EF 24 to 105 millimeters full
frame zoom lens is next on our list I
just want to take a very brief look at
it mainly because I sometimes use it for
my YouTube videos with its maximum
aperture of f4 over the whole Zoom range
it's not particularly Photon hungry but
it always produces excellent image
sharpness which made me curious about
how small the wavefront errors in a high
quality lens actually are
it was measured in the same way as the F
1.2 lens so in outer collimation and
here are the wavefront errors at the
focal length settings of 24 millimeters
50 millimeters and 105 millimeters the
largest waveform errors are found at 105
millimeters focal distance where this
Trail ratio has dropped to 0.6 which by
the way is still a very decent value for
a lens
in the center of the range its
performance is basically diffraction
limited so concluding this lens performs
well in the full Zoom range that is of
course within all the limitations of the
current testing method
if you made it this far into the video
you're probably more than averagely
interested in Optics so for this last
part I thought I'd present measurements
that I did on microscope objectives all
objectives presented here are so called
Infinity corrected objectives and this
means that they are designed to work in
combination with a so-called tube lens
rather than create an image directly
like is the case with proximity
corrected objectives
since Infinity corrected objectives
basically project their image at
Infinity this allows us to correctly use
the outer collimation configuration for
testing
unlike camera lenses microscope
objectives aren't specified by focal
length and maximal focal distance to
aperture ratio instead they're
characterized by magnification and
numerical aperture and I'll very briefly
discuss these two aspects first
magnification describes the ratio
between the object size and the image
size that a particular microscope
objective is designed for you can of
course try to use it at a different
magnification by changing both the lens
object distance and the lens image
distance but if you do that it will not
perform optimally and this is important
because microscope Optics is required to
work close to the theoretical best
performance
so in this sense a microscope objective
is a bit different from a camera lens
which is basically designed to give you
acceptable image quality over a wide
range of object to lens distances
now specifying a high magnification is
only useful if the sharpness in the
image keeps up with the magnification
that is specified and that is why the
magnification and numerical aperture of
objectives are related because numerical
aperture is a key parameter for
resolving small features
by definition the numerical aperture is
equal to the refractive index of the
medium that contains the object times
the sine of the maximum angle Theta at
which light originating from the object
can be captured this means that
numerical aperture increases with the
refractive index of the medium and with
the value of theta
now since all the objectives I will
discuss today are intended for using air
and not in water or oil we can simplify
things because the refractive index of
air is around one
so for now we can just ignore the
refractive index which means that the
numerical aperture in all cases
discussed here is just equal to the sine
of theta
the exact reason why numerical aperture
is the key parameter for achieving a
high sharpness is quite fascinating but
it's kind of a rabbit hole which I don't
want to dive in now
today I will just show you the formula
so the size of the smallest features
that can theoretically be resolved by a
microscope objective are proportional to
a constant times the wavelength of light
divided by the numerical aperture and
this means that it's possible to resolve
smaller features by either using a
shorter wavelength of light or use a
higher numerical aperture
this relationship explains why
magnification and numerical aperture are
so closely related in the specification
of microscope objectives because
attempting to pair a high magnification
with a low numerical aperture is pretty
useless it will just result in a
magnified image of pore sharpness
let's have a look at the measurements on
this Nikon 10 times objective with a
numerical aperture of 0.3 here is an
image of the wavefront error of this
objective and it shows us that the
errors are in fact very small the
wavefront is accurate within seven
hundredths of a wavelength for the
entire aperture and this Trail is 0.99
which is looking great so the major
contribution of the surface area is
actually a very slight spherical
aberration but all in all it's really a
top quality piece
now let's examine a different objective
like this 20 times Leica flu or tar with
a numerical aperture of 0.5 and do the
same waveform measurement
interestingly the spherical aberration
in this objective is noticeably more
pronounced both the peaked Valley Arrow
as well as a strail ratio is only just
on the good side of the diffraction
limit now it might be tempting to
conclude that this objective is not as
good as the previous one but that's
actually not the case the reason behind
the spherical aberration is in this
particular number that can be found on
the objective the number represents the
optimum coverslip thickness in
millimeters for this objective
so what the manufacturer assumes is that
you're going to use a glass coverslip
when you use your microscope and it has
therefore already compensated the
optical properties for a specific glass
thickness
now you might think huh 0.70 millimeters
of glass thickness how is that ever
going to influence the focus and indeed
with low numerical aperture Optics there
will generally not be a problem however
with increasing numerical aperture even
a gloss plate this thin can introduce a
significant spherical abrasion this is
Illustrated in this Ray tracing figure
for a numerical aperture of 0.7 in a
perfect optic all rays will end in a
single point but add a cover gloss and
certainly the area where the Rays end up
has significant size
now of course the previous waveform
measurement was done without a cover
slip so the question is what happens if
we add a cover slip in the light path I
quickly try this with a gloss thickness
of 0.60 millimeters so quite close to
the optimum value and it resulted in
this measurement it reduced the
spherical aberration quite a bit and so
this is something to realize when you
use a high numerical aperture objective
that it can only perform at its Peak
Performance when used in combination
with the cover slip thickness specified
so a few years ago I bought this
unmarked Nikon 20 times blonde Apple OEM
objective for use in my maskless wafer
stepper these Nikon objectives can be
purchased on eBay for around a hundred
dollars a piece and are widely available
it was in perfect shape when it got here
but when I started using it something
was a bit off depending on how I use it
exactly
now when I published the video on the
Master's waiver stepper people at the
Forum called photo
macrography.net made me aware of the
fact that these particular types of
objectives aren't optically the same as
the corresponding standard Nikon
microscope objectives they're actually
modified versions that are designed for
a different cover slip thickness
the forms that on this subject mentioned
that these perform better when used in
combination with two or three cover
slips and since I now have an
interferometer available let's see if we
can narrow this value down a bit further
here is the spherical aberration of the
objective without a cover slip the
wavefront error is one lobda so without
a correction it will certainly perform
very poorly
and here I summarize the individual
wavefront measurements for zero
one two
three and four cover slips
I think the effect of adding more glass
is pretty clear
now you can see that the wavefront error
sort of flips over between two and three
coverslips of glass thickness
now what we can do is take for example
the peak to Value spherical abrasion
from these measurements and plot the
values as a function of the glass
thickness in a graph and by fitting a
line through these data we find that a
minimum aberration is found at around
0.42 or 0.43 millimeters and this
thickness is right between two and three
copper slips like was stated on the
Forum here is a similar graph that I
made for the maximum still ratio which
actually yields exactly the same outcome
so if we were to add 0.42 millimeters of
glass sheet when using it we can
effectively get rid of the huge
spherical aberration completely and use
this objective at its maximum
performance level again
okay we finally come to the end of the
video I hope I gave you some ideas of
how interferometry can be used for
optical testing anyway thanks for
watching
foreign
[Music]