hey everyone today I want to talk about
Optical interferometry a method that is
frequently used to measure the
properties of optical components and
systems
what initially made me want to do a
video about this subject is this zygo
interferometer that I bought a while ago
secondhand
a new instrument of this type is
financially far out of my reach and I
must admit that this one wasn't a
bargain either but the thing is I wanted
to own a high quality interferometer for
a long time if only to get away from the
do-it-yourself setups that I've used so
far and since these instruments are not
abundantly available secondhand I just
had to take this rare opportunity to buy
one
in case you have no idea what this
instrument is with it you can very
accurately measure the shape of flat and
spherical Optical interfaces like the
ones you find on lenses and mirrors and
with accurately I mean in the nanometer
range
but not only that you can also measure
the performance of complete Optical
systems so a good interferometer is an
indispensable tool for anyone involved
in Optical fabrication because in the
end the quality of your Optics is mainly
limited by the quality of your testing
methods
this particular instrument was produced
by zygo in August of 1996 it was sold to
Philips Electronics in Eindhoven where
it was used to check the surface shape
of lenses of special Optical disk drives
from what I understood some of these
lenses were produced from small polished
glass balls and these were cut in pieces
and then transformed into very short
focal distance lenses now at some point
the activity was transferred to a
Phillips spin-off called anterion and
the interferometer was sold to an
employee who basically stored it for a
couple of years he then sold it to me
together with a black and white Monitor
and the transmission sphere that was
used to test the lenses
in this video I'll first discuss the
principle behind interferometry and then
we'll take a look at the layout of the
instrument and how it works exactly and
in an upcoming video I'll show you how I
pimped the instrument a bit with a
modern CCD camera
as I said earlier in Optics manufacturer
interferometry is a frequently used
method to characterize both Optical
surfaces as well as complete systems and
the method is based on analyzing
interference patterns and extract
so-called wavefront information from
them and I will discuss the meaning of
the word wavefront in a second
interferometry is an extremely sensitive
and accurate method that can be used to
establish the general shape of an
interface but also things like waviness
or even surface roughness it does also
have some limitations the measurement
ranges generally fairly limited to
several microns also it's unsuitable for
interfaces that contain sharp step-like
height features because these cannot be
unambiguously identified and so in
general interferometry is most accurate
when the surfaces we want to test are
fairly smooth
now I just mentioned the word wavefront
which I think is not a trivial concept I
guess we've all experienced wavefronts
at some points in our lives but I'm not
referring to those in Optics away from
this actually a continuous set of points
that have identical phase so what does
that mean well from a classical
Viewpoint light is an electromagnetic
wave that harmonically oscillates and
propagates in space and at any given
point in this process the electric and
magnetic field components can be
described by the Maxwell equations so
here I've tried to schematically draw
the electromagnetic field in a somewhat
larger volume and if you examine the
phase of these waves you can identify
planes where the face of the
electromagnetic field is identical and
the continuous set of points that have
the same phase value is called away
front
one property of a wavefront is that its
shape is always transverse or
perpendicular to the local direction of
wave propagation here this is
Illustrated for a few differently shaped
wavefronts where the arrows indicate the
direction of wave propagation now in
general phase relationships for
different points in space are only well
defined when the waves have one specific
wavelength and if we want to do
interferometry it's vital that the light
we use is of one particular wavelength
which is also called monochromatic light
and in the rest of this video I'll
assume that the light used is more or
less monochromatic
a frequently used way to generate
monochromatic radiation is by means of a
laser and this is because the process of
stimulated emission which takes place in
the laser cavity favors the generation
of light in a very narrow wavelength
range also the wavefront exiting the
laser cavity is virtually flat over the
aperture and because the light has an
extremely well defined wavelength in
other words it has a very narrow
spectral bandwidth phase relationships
in the field exiting the laser can be
preserved over long distances
another way to say this is that lasers
have a long coherence length which is
generally between half a meter up to
several kilometers for certain special
types of lasers
in practice this means that if we take
two points A and B in the light path and
we look at the variations in the phase
difference between the two points we
will find that these will be relatively
small and the distance over which
variations in Phase remain acceptable is
called the coherence length as you can
see from this equation the coherence
length LC is inversely proportional to
the spectral bandwidth Delta Nu of the
light source and so light sources with a
very narrow emission line will generally
have a long coherence length
another source of monochromatic light
frequently used in interferometry is the
low pressure sodium lamp which mainly
generates light in a narrow emission
band at 589 nanometers however the
spectral bandwidth of the sodium
emission line is much broader than that
of lasers and the phase relationships
generally only hold over distances
smaller than a millimeter
now measuring the shape of a waveform
directly in the visible part of the
electromagnetic spectrum is not easy and
that is because of the high frequencies
involved for electromagnetic radiation
of longer wavelengths like for example
radio waves we can measure the phase of
the alternating Fields directly and that
is because the oscillations have
relatively low frequency say generally
somewhere in the mega or gigahertz range
and so we can point a bunch of antennas
to the sky measure the electromagnetic
signals that are received in each of
them and then establish the shape of the
wavefront for a particular frequency by
looking for phase correlations and based
on this information we can identify the
exact direction from which the radiation
is emitted
but the visible light has a frequency
more than a thousand times higher than
even the highest frequency radio waves
and for frequencies this high it's
technically infeasible to measure phase
directly for an oscillating
electromagnetic field
however what we can easily measure with
Optical detectors like CCD or CMOS
sensors is spatial intensity variations
and that is where interferometry comes
in instead of trying to measure the
phase in light directly this method
works by studying the interference
patterns resulting from the addition of
a second wavefront that has a known
shape
let me start by showing you a very
simple example of how this works in
light
for this experiment we need a
monochromatic light source and a flat
surface as a light source we'll use a
sodium lamp and for the surface we'll
use a flat Optical test glass
now a typical air gloss interface
reflects about four percent of the
incident light and with a uniform light
source we observe a uniform reflection
let's now place two differently shaped
surfaces on top of this reference
surface for evaluation and what we now
observe is that these objects show two
different interference patterns the part
of the left shows straight lines with
equal spacing and I wanted to write this
place these curved lines or circular
fringes depending on the exact surface
orientation now it's these intensity
variations that actually contain
detailed information about the
difference in shape between the
reference surface and the two surfaces
under tests and we just need to know how
to interpret what we see exactly
so what do we see well let me explain
with an animation I admit the following
is a simplification and it's not
correctly visualizing the physics but
it's actually quite illustrative here is
away from that has just reflected off a
flat reference surface so this wavefront
is basically also flat and so the image
shows a 2d cross-section of the flat
Optical wavefront
now we place a sensor in the path of the
light we can measure the intensity and
what we observe is that it's basically
the same everywhere and this tells us
exactly nothing about the shape of the
wavefront
now let's add a second wavefront that
has reflected of a second surface that
is slightly tilted in this example the
wavefront is also flat and what we
observe is that the intensity now
becomes non-uniform and this is caused
by constructive and destructive
interference between the two reflected
wavefronts at the second interface here
the electromagnetic field is the linear
sum of the contributions of the fields
of the two wavefronts and so in some
points where these contributions are
always in Phase they add up on the other
hand in places where the two are exactly
out of phase the field contributions
cancel each other out and if they are of
equal amplitude effectively the
resulting field becomes zero
in the case of two flat wavefronts we
will observe linear and equally spaced
fringes and the density of the
interference pattern itself is dependent
on the wedge or angle between the two
surfaces and the position of the fringes
is dependent on the distance between the
two surfaces now you might think that
linear and equally spaced fringes are
indicative for the presence of two flat
surfaces and that's partly correct but
two curved wavefronts with exactly the
same radius of curvature will actually
also display linear and equally spaced
fringes when displays are tilted
however when two waveforms have
different radii this results in curve
fringes and this is for example the case
when we have a flat and a spherical
wavefront interfering or when we have
two spherical waveforms that have a
different radius of curvature so I guess
it's important to realize that the
observed interference pattern only gives
us information about differences in
wavefront shape
the example just shown with the Sodium
lamp we only observe interference
between the interfaces when they're
placed very close together and that is
because of the limited coherence length
of the light so whether we can see a
clear interference pattern is dependent
on whether stable phase relationships
exists between the reflections coming
off the two surfaces at the point where
they start interfering and this means
that with a coherence length smaller
than a millimeter the surfaces need to
be quite close to each other in order to
observe interference fringes
now I just stated that in constructive
interference the electromagnetic fields
add up and in destructive interference
the two contributions cancel each other
out so what does this mean for intensity
well light intensity is equivalent to
the power per unit of surface and so
it's actually not the same thing as the
magnitude of the electronic field in
fact intensity scales with the square of
this field and so if we have two
reflections of equal magnitude say both
are four percent this means that for the
location of constructive interference
the intensity could be four times as
high and that is actually what is
generally observed in interference
patterns that the intensity in the
bright areas is much brighter than the
sum of the two individual intensities
but of course if we look on average the
intensity over the whole area will still
be equal to the sum of the two
individual intensities
anyway enough background let's return to
the zygote interferometer itself and
take a peek under the hood to see what's
going on inside
in order to do that we need to remove
two different Lids the outer one is made
of plastic and it's basically just
cosmetic and the second one is made out
of aluminum sheet metal and it is
intended as RF shielding for the
electronics inside
the first thing you notice is that it
isn't awfully full inside there is a
helium neon laser with its high voltage
power supply then there are a few
Optical components like a steering
mirror for a laser beam a variable
filter that can be moved mechanically
using a rod and this Rod also operates a
switch that activates either of two PCB
cameras that can also be found in this
top part of the interferometer
and the cameras by the way have CCD
chips of about four by six millimeter in
size and are fairly low resolution
now both cameras have lenses mounted in
front of them and one of the cameras is
above a tiny beam splitter and the other
one is above a diffuser with a Crosshair
printed on it
in the bottom compartment behind the lid
here we find the mains 12 volt DC power
supply a large beam splitter a mirror
under 45 degrees and a four inch
collimation lens and apart from a few
brackets and mounts that hold the Optics
together that is basically it
so you might wonder why was this thing
the price of a luxury car back in 1996
well apart from I suspect a healthy
profit margin there are several reasons
of course it's not really a mass
manufactured item but another reason is
that every component inside appears to
be of very high quality take for example
the helium neon laser according to the
label the tube has been specifically
selected for this type of instrument why
well if we look at the specification of
the coherence length of the
interferometer we see that it's larger
than 100 meters this means that the
wavelength variations in the laser light
need to be extremely low so that the
phase relationships hold over distances
of more than 100 meters now I calculated
what this means in terms of frequency
stability and found that variations in
the frequency of the light cannot be
more than 2 times 10 to the minus seven
percent and so this means that not just
any random laser will do
so let me take you through the
functionality of all the optical
components step by step using schematics
here is the helium mule laser which
outputs a highly coherent beam of light
and the direction of the beam can be
optimized with this small steering
mirror after which the beam goes through
a variable attenuation filter now this
filter allows for adjustment of the
general brightness of the laser beam and
after having passed the attenuation
filter the beam is going into a gradient
index lens which is connected to a very
small beam splitter
now a gradient index lens is a small
glass rod that contains a gradient in
refractive index that runs from the
center to the edge of the rod and since
the refractive index has the highest
value in the center the optical
wavefront in the laser beam is gradually
delayed more towards the center of the
rod and the waveform therefore becomes
curved which effectively results in
focusing of the light into a tight focal
point and after passing this focal point
the beam expands again into a nicely
spherical wavefront
a small beam splitter sends the
spherical waveform into the partially
reflective surface of a second much
larger beam splitter and this surface
reflects the light towards a collimation
lens where the light exits the
instrument
the function of the collimation lens is
to convert the spherical wavefront into
a flat wavefront of four inches in
diameter and this flat waveform can
serve as the basis for all kinds of
interferometric tests for example we can
place two partially reflective flat
interfaces into this output beam one
being the reference interface and one
being the interface that we'd like to
test for flatness and due to the large
coherence length of the light more than
100 meters these interfaces don't have
to be necessarily very close together
the light reflecting of these surfaces
is directed back into the interferometer
approximately along the same path as it
came from goes through a small beam
splitter again and then is collimated
and projected on the CCD chip and this
allows us to observe the interference
pattern between the two Reflections and
evaluate this visually on the monitor
now to steer the light off both the
reference and test surface exactly back
through the tiny beam splitter here is
pretty hard and you don't see anything
with camera one until things are almost
perfectly aligned so to make life a lot
easier the people at zygo edit this
alignment functionality to the system
part of the light from the reflections
can pass this larger beam splitter and
this part continues straight on it's
reflected at 90 degrees angle and then
reaches the glass diffuser plate that
contains a Crosshair pattern
because this diffuser plate is exactly
at the focal distance of the collimation
lens the reflections create tiny spots
here and their positions can be observed
by camera 2 that is only intended for
alignment purposes now this alignment
unit has a much larger field of view and
what we can do now is simply align the
position of the surface reflection such
that they are at the center of the
Crosshair and when that's the case the
system is also automatically aligned on
camera one we can immediately observe an
interferogram
now the interferometers that I made
myself did not have this kind of feature
and I must admit that this really makes
aligning Optics a piece of cake
here you see the location of the
collimation lens viewed from the outside
of the instrument in front of it is an
adjustment mechanism that is intended
for mounting various reference surfaces
to the interferometer directly like for
example the f.7 D5 transmission sphere
that came with interferometer
the adjustment mechanism has two degrees
of freedom which are tip and tilt and
this allows the angle of the
transmission reference to be oriented
with respect to the surface under test
so when testing Optical components you
generally test the surface shape before
the interfaces get coated and so in the
case of glosses means that they reflect
around four percent of the incident
light
so the transmission reference also needs
to reflect around four percent back into
the interferometer to get high contrast
fringes
not to test spherical surfaces you need
a spherical reference surface that
somehow reflects four percent of the
light exiting the infrometer right back
into the instrument
here I've drawn a schematic of the
inside of a transmission sphere assembly
to show you how that is achieved
the reference surface is the last
interface of the assembly here indicated
in yellow and all the other surfaces are
anti-reflection coated for the laser
wavelength
but even more importantly they're also
designed in such a way that the Light
reaches the reference interface exactly
perpendicular and this means that it's
the only interface in the transmission
sphere that sends a reflection back
where it came from and then enters the
interferometer as a collimated beam and
of course
96 of the light continues onto the
surface under test which also reflects
around four percent and so we observe
the interference occurring between these
two interfaces
with a spherical transmission reference
we can test convex as well as concave
optics for convex Optics only radii is
smaller than the radius of the
transmission sphere itself can be tested
and for concave Optics the only
limitation for the radius to be tested
is that it should be less than half of
the maximum coherence length of the
light source that we use which is in
this case 50 meters
now I want to save most of the
experiments that I had in mind for
another video but let's just do one
simple experiment for this test we'll
just use the flat wavefront exiting the
instrument and what we'll try to measure
is the difference in shape between the
two surfaces of a zero to your test
Clause this test class has one side
which I know is very flat around 120th
of a wavelength and this is going to be
our reference interface but the other
side is somewhat less flat and what
we'll try to find out is how much that
is
the two interfaces are spaced 20
millimeters apart and both reflect
around four percent of the incident
light so we can just place the disc in
the beam exiting the interferometer
align the position of the two
Reflections simultaneously and then look
at the interference pattern and this is
what it looks like as you can see we get
a nice and clear interference pattern
which by the way is extremely stable
with no effects of vibrations from the
environment and that is because the two
surfaces are basically mechanically
connected to each other by a solid piece
of zero Doer
now the small circular spots are just
dust particles in the optical path and
these are not important for our
evaluation
all the information about the different
in shape and orientation between the two
surfaces is contained in the four more
or less vertical fringes and because we
know that one side is almost perfectly
flat any curvature in The Fringe pattern
is a result of non-flatness of the
second interface
so let's try to evaluate this pattern
visually the most obvious feature is of
course the presence of the four vertical
fringes that indicate that there is a
wedge between the two interfaces in the
horizontal Direction and we can evaluate
how large this wedge is based on the
number of fringes it's a little over
four lobda wavefront meaning that there
is a wedge half of that between the two
surfaces so just two wavelengths y half
well that is because in reflection any
deviations in surface shape lead to
twice the deviation in the wave front
shape and so deviations in the surface
shape are only half of that observed in
the wavefront
now since the wavelength of the laser is
633 nanometers and the wedge is two
lobbed up between the two surfaces this
would mean a gradient in distance of
approximately 1.3 microns but there is a
little catch in this case because we are
comparing two surfaces with zero during
between them we should actually use the
wavelength in this material which means
that we should divide the wavelength in
air or vacuum by the refractive index of
zero deer which is 1.54
so this means that the wedge is actually
only 840 nanometers but which side is
thicker it's actually quite hard to tell
as for which we would see the same type
of interference pattern in either case
so at this point we just don't know
okay let's for a moment focus on the
curvature of the fringes now which
indicates a difference in the radius
between the two surfaces and if we look
at how much the curvature in the fringes
deviates from straight lines we see that
it's largest here in the center it's
about 0.4 times The Fringe spacing which
translates to 0.4 wavelengths of height
difference between the edge and the
center of the disc
for the surface error which again is
half of that we find 0.2 wavelengths now
since we also need to use the wavelength
inside zero do here this means that the
surface curvature is 0.2 times the
wavelength divided by the refractive
index which results in a value of 82
nanometers
but in which direction is the curve is
the surface under test 82 nanometers
concave or convex as for the direction
of the wedge there is no easy way to
tell so now we end up with these four
configurations of which only one can be
correct
with a little logic though you could at
this point already discard two of these
as infeasible but of course you want to
know exactly which configuration of the
four is correct right
so if that's indeed the case figure it
out yourself you just need two more
pieces of information here is a first
hint if I press my finger against the
back side of the disk so the service and
the test we can observe that the
interferogram changes due to the
temperature increase of the material by
the heat of my finger locally it's only
a few degrees Celsius higher but the
effect is very noticeable because we are
measuring in the nanometer range
now the second piece of information you
need is about the expansion coefficient
of the material as you can see from the
specifications of zero zero it can be
either positive or negative
but this piece of 02 has a positive
coefficient of thermal expansion which
means it expands with temperature
increase and with these two additional
pieces of information it's possible to
tell which of these four options is
correct now the first person to make a
comment with the correct answer and of
course why owns the pinned comment
okay so the letter was a very brief
explanation of how you can evaluate
interferograms visually and the above
example was actually relatively easy
imagine your interferogram looks
something like this or this in these
cases it would be quite a bit more
challenging to make accurate statements
about the exact surface shape
and this is why in the next video about
the subject I have replaced the current
analog camera with a high resolution IP
camera and this allows for a very
detailed evaluation of the
interferograms using software
with the help of this software we can
measure wedges angles surface curvature
and even the effect of warm fingers very
accurately also we'll take a look at how
to measure the shape of various Optical
surfaces and the quality of lens
assemblies so hopefully I'll see you in
the next video again
[Music]
thank you
bye bye